Preliminary Inventory of the Alex Inkeles papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Alex Inkeles papers
1941-2003
85005
Inkeles, Alex, 1920-
549 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes, 6 card file boxes, 4 data tapes, and 32 linear feet of volumes (265 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers contain the American sociologist's materials relating to research on social change in the twentieth century, as well as the promotion of international educational exchanges and intellectual cooperation, especially between the United States and China. Includes documentation associated with research projects conducted by Inkeles, research material and statistical data for the book by Alex Inkeles and David H. Smith, Becoming Modern: Individual Change in Six Developing Countries (Cambridge, Mass., 1974), relating to the transition of social attitudes of individuals in developing countries, and materials pertaining to his teaching career in correspondence, writings, notes, memoranda, reports, printed matter, and sound recordings.
Administrative Information
Access
Boxes 517-519 are closed. A portion of the collection is stored off-site: boxes 1-51, 52-79, 82-125, and 131-372. It may be possible to have a limited number of boxes brought to the archives reading room for examination. A minimum of two days notice is required. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information. The remainder of the collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985, with additional increments through 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Born in Brooklyn, New York, Inkeles received an A.B. degree in 1941 and an A.M. in 1946 from Cornell University. He received a Ph.D. in 1949 from Columbia University, publishing Public Opinion in Soviet Russia: A Study in Mass Persuasion in 1950.
A professor of sociology at Harvard University from 1957 to 1971, he published What Is Sociology? in 1964 and Social Change in Soviet Russia in 1968.
From 1972 on, Inkeles was a professor of sociology at Stanford University and a senior fellow at the Hoover Institution. Inkeles was an expert on political behavior, modernization, social psychology, and national character. His research focused on the social structure of an emerging worldwide society and cross-national comparative studies. Inkeles published Becoming Modern: Individual Change in Six Developing Countries in 1974 and Exploring Individual Modernity in 1983.
Inkeles has held numerous fellowships including the Center for Advanced Study in Behavioral Sciences in Stanford, California from 1955 to 1956 a Guggenheim fellowship for study in Israel and the United Kingdom from 1977 to 1978, and a National Academy of Sciences fellowship in 1992. He was also a Fulbright scholar in Greece in 1977 and in Chile in 1985.
He was elected to three of the most distinguished honorary societies in America: the American Academy of Arts and Sciences in 1962, the American Philosophical Society in 1972, and the National Academy of Sciences in 1981.
Alex Inkeles passed away on July 9, 2010.
Sources: "Alex Inkeles, Senior Fellow" Hoover Institution. http://www.hoover.org/fellows/alex-inkeles Accessed January 6, 2012
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers consist largely of documentation associated with research projects conducted by Inkeles, a prominent American sociologist, as well as materials pertaining to his teaching career. There are numerous papers and articles written by Inkeles, writings by others, and printed matter relating to sociology and to international geographic studies of locations such as the Soviet Union, China, and India.
A large section of material concerns the Harvard Project on the Socio-Cultural Aspects of Development (later known as the Harvard Project on Social and Cultural Aspects of Development), a large study headed by Inkeles that collected data on the basis of interviews made in Argentina, Chile, India, Israel, Nigeria, and East Pakistan (now Bangladesh). The data was subsequently used as the basis for a 1974 book by Inkeles, Becoming Modern: Individual Change in Six Developing Countries.
A variety of Inkeles' writings include a chronological section of article reprints, various research materials, drafts, papers, and book chapters. Also included are drafts and research data for Inkeles' books Exploring Individual Modernity and the edited volume, Sociology: An Introduction.
The papers also include materials related to Inkeles research projects, including collected background materials, data sets, and draft writings on topics such as "Quality of Life," "National Character," and "Adolescence."
Material on Inkeles' academic teaching career consists of lecture notes and course materials for sociology classes, dissertations and theses written by students, academic administrative material, and documentation on his involvement in organizations such as the Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Smith, David Horton.; Social change.; Civilization, Modern.; Sociology.; Developing countries--Social conditions.; Intellectual cooperation.; United States--Relations--China.; China--Relations--United States.; Education.; Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China (U.S.)
Collection Contents
- Becoming Modern: Individual Change in Six Developing Countries, (Harvard University Press, 1974) research material, relating to the transition of social attitudes of individuals in developing countries, circa 1965-1974. Includes computer printouts of statistics, codebooks, memoranda, notes and 4 computer data tapes. Volumes of statistics arranged in a double numeric-alpha sequence denoted by the project from 1-15. I.e.: 1A-3C or 15C-1F (Box 1-44, 32 linear feet of volumes)
- Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China, correspondence, notes, memoranda, reports, studies, minutes, charts, financial statements, and printed matter relating to activities of the Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China in promoting educational exchanges and intellectual cooperation between the United States and China, 1984-1989 (Box 45-50)
- Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China, correspondence, memoranda, minutes, and reports relating to activities of the Committee for Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China, particularly its field station in Shandong province, 1986-1990 (Box 51)
- Harvard University Project on the Socio-Cultural Aspects of Development (HUPSCAD), 1963-1964 (Box 52-61)
  - Completed questionnaires from interviews conducted in Pakistan, 1963-1964 (Box 52-61)
    - Nos. 701-800, 1964 (Box 52)
    - Nos. 801-900, 1964 (Box 53)
    - Nos. 501-600, 1963-1964 (Box 54)
    - Nos. 301-400, 1964 (Box 55)
    - Nos. 201-300, 1964 (Box 56)
    - Nos. 601-633, 1964 (Box 57)
    - Nos. 936-1000, 1964 (Box 57)
    - Nos. 401-500, 1964 (Box 58)
    - Nos. 901-934, 1964 (Box 59)
    - Nos. 634-700, 1964 (Box 59)
    - Nos. 101-200, 1964 (Box 60)
    - Nos. 1-100, 1964 (Box 61)
- Exploring Individual Modernity (Columbia University Press, 1983) (Box 62-79)
  - Drafts, correspondence, notes, studies, bibliographies, tables, and charts used as research material, 1965-1982 (Box 62-79)
- Computer printouts of data relating to analysis of team leadership, 1987 (Box 80-81)
- Educational Institutions and International Labor Conference, Michigan State University, conference papers, 1962 (Folder 82: 1)
- Russia Research Center, Harvard University, focus studies, data summaries, 1953 (Folder 82: 2)
- Harvard Project on the Socio-Cultural Aspects of Development, 1963-1967 (Folder 82:)
  - Standard English version of questionnaire, 1966 (Folder 82: 3)
  - Small R-matrices: Argentina and India, 1967 (Folder 82: 4)
  - Standard English version of questionnaire, 1964 (Folder 83: 1-2)
  - Field director's report, 1966 (Folder 83: 3)
  - Listing of behavioral items, 1966 (Folder 83: 4)
  - Pakistan: Factory reports, 1963-1964 (Folder 84: 1)
  - Scale book, 1965 (Folder 84: 2)
- Files on migration, 1965 (Folder 84: 3-18)
- Russian Research Center, Harvard University, focus studies, 1953 (Box 85)
  - Data tables prepared by Irv Rosow, 1953 (Folder 85: 1-3)
  - Data tables prepared by Irv Rosow, 1953 (Folder 86: 1)
  - A-schedules, 1953 (Folder 86: 2)
  - Harvard Project on the Socio-Cultural Aspects of Development, 1965-1971 (Box 86)
  - General description and questionnaire, 1967 (Folder 86: 3)
  - Staff meeting notes, 1965 (Folder 86: 4)
  - Bibliographic material prepared by Natalie J. Sokoloff, 1966 (Folder 87: 1-3)
  - Selected papers, 1966 (Folder 88: 1)
  - General description and reprints, 1967 (Folder 88: 2)
  - Basic data information, 1967 (Folder 88: 3)
  - Index to alphabetical items, 1967 (Folder 88: 4)
  - Independent variable index, 1967 (Folder 89: 1)
  - Scales, 1967 (Folder 89: 2)
  - Career patterns, 1967 (Folder 89: 3)
  - Index-all countries, 1967 (Folder 90: 1)
  - Key phrases, 1967 (Folder 90: 2)
  - Scale reliabilities, 1971 (Folder 90: 3)
  - Cards 86-87, 92-93, 1967 (Folder 90: 4)
  - All countries: sequential key phrases, 1967 (Folder 90: 5)
  - Scale codebook, volume one, two, 1967 (Folder 91: 1-2)
  - Nigeria codebook, 1967 (Folder 91: 3)
  - Pakistan codebook, 1967 (Folder 92: 1)
  - Non-IV project reports, 1968 (Box 92)
    - volume one-two, 1968 (Folder 92: 2-3)
    - volume three-five, 1968 (Folder 93: 1-3)
    - volume six-seven, 1968 (Folder 94: 1-2)
- Articles and papers by Alex Inkeles, 1946-1976 (Folder 95: 1-19)
- Chapters written by Alex Inkeles for edited volumes, 1973-1974 (Folder 96: 1-2)
- Correspondence, 1963-1971 (Folder 96: 3-5)
- Student papers, 1951-1974 (Folder 96: 6-15)
- Student papers, 1962-1969 (Folder 97: 1-7)
- Articles and papers by Alex Inkeles, including correspondence, 1949-1968 (Folder 97: 8-19)
- Writings by others, 1957-1961 (Folder 97: 20-21)
- Files on polling, 1948-1958 (Folder 98: 1-5)
- Correspondence, 1958-1965 (Folder 98: 6)
- Roper Center report, 1963 (Folder 98: 7)
- National character bibliography, 1953 (Folder 98: 8)
- Memos by Jay Greenfield, 1950 (Folder 98: 9)
- Seminar outline, 1950 (Folder 98: 10)
- File on social psychology, 1961 (Folder 98: 11)
- Personality profile study, 1958 (Folder 99: 1)
- Lecture notes for sociology classes taught by Alex Inkeles, 1954-1959 (Folder 99: 2-13)
- Social Structure of the World project, 1973 (Folder 99: 14-15)
- Lecture notes and reading lists for sociology classes taught by Alex Inkeles, 1954-1959 (Folder 100: 1-20)
- Assignments, exams, reading lists, and student records for sociology classes taught by Alex Inkeles, 1953-1969 (Folder 101: 1-23)
- Assignments, exams, reading lists, and student records for sociology classes taught by Alex Inkeles, 1965-1969 (Folder 102: 1-12)
- Assignments, exams, reading lists, and student records for sociology classes taught by Alex Inkeles, 1949-1967 (Folder 103: 1-14)
- Lecture notes and reading lists for sociology classes taught by Alex Inkeles, 1950-1965 (Folder 104: 1-14)
- Dissertations and theses by students, 1965-1977 (Box 105-107)
  - Jensen, Gene, 1973 (Folder 105: 1-2)
  - Gross, Leslie Jay, 1965 (Folder 106: 1)
  - Gollay, Elinor, 1966 (Folder 106: 2)
  - Jarry, Roberto, 1977 (Folder 106: 3)
  - Lawrence, William Ward, 1965 (Folder 106: 4)
  - Cunningham, Ineke, 1971 (Folder 106: 5)
  - Katz, Marlaine Lockheed, 1972 (Folder 107: 1)
  - Howard, Leslie Lawrence, 1974 (Folder 107: 2-3)
  - Viveros, Elena, 1977 (Folder 107: 4)
- Chapter written by Alex Inkeles for edited volume, 1976 (Folder 108: 1)
- Writings by others, 1963-1976 (Folder 108: 2-3)
- Correspondence and papers, 1972-1974 (Folder 108: 1-5)
- Datebook, 1977 (Folder 108: 6)
- Kentucky codebook, C 1-17, Nebraska Farmers/US Airmen (Folder 108: 7)
- Kornitauser Study "Mental Health of the Industrial Worker" codebook (Folder 108: 8)
- Becoming Modern: Individual Change in Six Developing Countries, research materials and codebooks, circa 1968-1974 (Box 109-120)
  - Harvard University Project on Socio-Cultural Aspects of Development questionnaire, complete English version (Folder 109: 1-2)
  - Master Work Deck codebook (Folder 109: 3)
  - Pakistan coding, sampling background (Folder 109: 4)
  - Israel/Pakistan, re-interview codes (Folder 109: 5)
  - Pakistan/Israel, re-interview codebook (Folder 109: 6)
  - Scale codebooks index: all countries (Folder 110: 1)
  - Argentina binary tape dictionary for sequential and scales tape and Argentina binary tape codebook (Folder 110: 2)
  - Argentina codebook cards #1-17, Spanish (Folder 110: 3)
  - STO Scales (Folder 110: 4)
  - Harvard Project of the Socio-Cultural Aspects of Development, Standard English version of the questionnaire (Folder 111: 1)
  - Argentina codebook, cards 1-17 (Folder 111: 2)
  - Israel codebook (Folder 111: 3)
  - India codebook (Folder 111: 4)
  - Nigeria codebook (Folder 112: 1)
  - Pakistan codebook, cards 1-17 (Folder 112: 2)
  - Project on Socio-Cultural Aspects of Development Book 1, questions and codes on cards 1-4 (Folder 112: 3)
  - Six Country scale codebook, copy I, Vol. I-II (Folder 113: 1-2)
  - Four Country student/main sample codebook, book 1-2, closed questions (Folder 113: 3-4)
  - All Countries, cards 30-40 and sequential/key phrases (Folder 114: 1)
  - Project on Socio-Cultural Aspects of Development, questions and codes on cards 5-17 with alphabetical index (Folder 114: 2-3)
  - Location of items, cards 5-8; by card and by alpha item 10 (Folder 114: 4)
  - New IM's, 1970 item coding: A, C, I, S, N, and P (Folder 114: 5)
  - Project on Socio-Cultural Aspects of Development questions and codes on cards 5-17, A-GO and ST-W (Corresponds to Roper Vols. II, IIIA, IIIB) (Folder 115: 1-2)
  - Index cards 25-26, all countries (Folder 115: 3)
  - IV's cards 1-4, Book 1-2 (Folder 116: 1-2)
  - Card 82 codebooks (Folder 116: 3-4)
  - HUPSCAD Tumin code book, items of interest (Folder 116: 5)
  - HUPSCAD Tumin code book, other items (Folder 116: 6)
  - Project on Socio-Cultural Aspects of Development, book V, Card 82 codebook (Folder 117: 1)
  - Card 86 codebook, all countries, copy 1 (Folder 117: 2)
  - Card 87, regression analysis guide (Folder 117: 3)
  - Card 98, All Countries, cross-tabs items/IVs (Folder 117: 4)
  - Scale book master, item/item correlations (Folder 117: 5-6)
  - National matching, work deck codebook, copy 2 and 3 (Folder 118: 1-2)
  - Match corrections and cross-national matches (Folder 118: 5)
  - Matching data: All Countries, copy III, Vol. 1 (Folder 118: 6-7)
  - Matching data: All Countries, copy III, Vol. 2 (Folder 119: 1-2)
  - Matching data: India, Chile, Argentina (original sheets) (Folder 119: 3-4)
  - Matching data: Nigeria, Pakistan, Israel (Folder 119: 5)
  - Learning curves, copy 2 (Folder 119: 6)
  - Miscellaneous matching information (Folder 120: 1-2)
  - National matching program match #52 (Folder 120: 3)
  - Copy of Files for Smith on Scale Analysis: 8/90. Includes dumps of original tapes of HUPSCAD data (Folder 120: 4)
  - Scale codebook: Israel, Nigeria, and Pakistan (Folder 120: 5)
- Materials relating to the edited volume, Sociology: an Introduction, 1976 (Box 120)
  - Outlines and correspondence, 1976 (Folder 121: 1-15)
  - Correspondence and drafts of chapters, 1976 (Folder 122: 1-39)
  - Correspondence and drafts of chapters, 1976 (Folder 123: 1-46)
  - Correspondence and drafts of chapters, 1976 (Folder 124: 1-28)
  - Correspondence and drafts of chapters, 1976 (Folder 125: 1-22)
- Harvard Project on the Socio-Cultural Aspects of Development, 1965 (Box 126)
  - Book of computer printouts, "Composite marginals-all countries, cards 5-8," 1965 (Folder 126: 1)
- Becoming Modern: Individual Change in Six Developing Countries, research materials, circa 1968-1974 (Folder 127-130:)
  - Anderson, Barbara A. "Internal Migration in a Modernizing Society: The Case of Late Nineteenth Century European Russia," and correspondence from Martha Puff (Folder 127: 1-3)
  - Alguero, Manuel S. "Individual Modernity and Lower-Class Fertility Behavior in Guatemala" (Folder 127: 4)
  - Almond and Varea, CFIA questionnaires (Folder 127: 5)
  - Andrews and Sardo "Migration and Migrants from Sedgwick County, Colorado" (Folder 127: 6)
  - Antonovsky, A. "Classification of Forms, Political Ideologies..." (Folder 127: 7)
  - Bell, Daniel "Call Me Ismael" (Folder 127: 8)
  - Bellah, Robert N. "Meaning and Modernization" (Folder 127: 9)
  - Bergthold, Gary D. and McClelland, David C. "The Impact of Peace Corps Teachers on Students in Ethiopia" (Folder 127: 10)
  - Bhat, K.S. "Preparation of Child for Modernization," India, 1970 (Folder 128: 1)
  - Bidwell and Vreeland, "College Education and Moral Orientations: An Organizational Approach" (Folder 128: 2)
  - Paul Burstein-"Social Structure, Political Parties and Political Socialization" (Folder 128: 3)
  - CIS research activities (Folder 128: 4)
  - The Center for Rural Development Purposes and Programs (Folder 128: 5)
  - Childe, Gordon, "The Urban Revolution" (Folder 128: 6)
  - CINTRA project, related projects, Brazil (Folder 128: 7)
  - Cohen, Alvin: "Economic Development and the Displacement of Peruvian Elites" (Folder 128: 8)
  - Wayne A. Cornelius, Jr., "Political Correlates of Migrant Assimilation in Mexican Urban Environments" (Folder 128: 9)
  - Cunningham/Inkeles, Puerto Rico study (Folder 128: 10)
  - David, Stanley, "Patterns in Management Organization and Ideology during Industrialization," Mexico (Ideology during Industrialization) (Folder 128: 11)
  - Dietz, Henry, Stanford University, "Assimilation and Politicization of Urban Squatter Migrants in Lima, Peru" (Folder 128: 12)
  - Dittman, F., "Cultural Constraints in the Acquisition of Achievement Motivation" (Folder 128: 13)
  - Duncan, Otis D., "Residential Areas and Differential Fertility" (Folder 128: 14)
  - Eder, Jim, abstract, "A Research Proposal Submitted to NIMH" (Folder 128: 15)
  - Eisenstadt, S.N. "Modernization and Conditions of Sustained Growth" and "Breakdowns of Modernization" (Folder 128: 16-17)
  - Espinola, J.C. "Urbanizacion, Estruetura Social, Sistema de Valores" (Folder 129: 1)
  - Estudio de Conflictos y Consenso (University of Venezuela) (Folder 129: 2)
  - Fischer, Claude, "Urbanism and Tolerance" (Folder 129: 3)
  - Freedman, Goldberg and Slesinger, "Fertility Expectations in the United States: 1963" (Folder 129: 4)
  - Freedman, Takashita and Sun, "Fertility and Family Planning in Taiwan: A Case Study..." (Folder 129: 5)
  - Frey, Fred, "Study of Conflict and Consensus" (Folder 129: 6)
  - Farrison, Lloyd, "The Ibos Go It Alone" (Folder 129: 7)
  - Gore, M.S. questionnaire (Folder 129: 8)
  - Hall, John W., "Changing Conceptions of the Modernization of Japan" (Folder 129: 9)
  - Hall, S.K., "National Institute for Personnel Resolution Modernization Project Questionnaire" (Folder 129: 10)
  - Halpern, Joel, "The Rural Revolution" (Folder 129: 11)
  - Halpern questionnaire (Folder 129: 12)
  - Heller, Porter, "Perceptions of Managerial Incentives, Satisfactions and Required Skills in Two National Samples" (Folder 129: 13)
  - Huntington, Samuel P., "Political Modernization: America vs. Europe" (Folder 129: 14)
  - OM Users, Inquiries/Requests for Materials: A-H (Folder 129: 15-17)
  - OM Users, Inquiries/Requests for Materials: I-Z (Folder 130: 1-4)
  - Turkish Village Survey: Interview Schedules (Folder 130: 5)
  - Turner, Arthur N., Management-Worker Relationships (Foreman) (Folder 130: 6)
  - UC Berkeley Institute of International Studies, Complex Traditional Societies in Transition (Folder 130: 7)
  - Vepa, Prasad, "UN Conference on Exploration and Peaceful Uses of Outer Space" (Folder 130: 8)
  - Vickery, Howard, "Chilean Students and Politics" (Folder 130: 9)
  - Volman, Sacha, "Latin American Experiments in Political and Economic Training" (Folder 130: 10)
  - WAPOR Newsletter 1970 (Folder 130: 11)
  - Weiner, Myron, "Theories of Modernization" (Folder 130: 12)
- Correspondence, writings, memoranda, proposals, studies, travel reports, minutes, and printed matter relating to Alex Inkeles' research and teaching activities and to his participation in various professional organizations, 1978-1991 (Box 131-207)
- Becoming Modern: Individual Change in Six Developing Countries, (Harvard University Press, 1974) (Box 208)
  - Data on various developing countries and a study conducted by Richard Suzman in Tunis, used as research material, 1966-1976 (Box 208)
- Exploring Individual Modernity (Columbia University Press, 1983) (Box 209-253)
  - Research material for and drafts and galleys, 1961-1992 (Box 209-253)
- Correspondence, speeches and writings, grant proposals, conference papers and proceedings, curriculum material, financial records, and printed matter relating to sociology, education of disadvantaged children, 1961-1992 (Box 209-253)
- Teaching activities and participation in various professional organizations, 1961-1992 (Box 209-253)
- Drafts of writings, correspondence, and memoranda relating to various aspects of sociology, 1979-1989 (Box 254-261)
- Correspondence, speeches and writings, memoranda, reports, and grant proposals relating to various aspects of sociology, 1963-1991 (Box 262-274)
- Correspondence, drafts of writings, working materials, and memoranda relating to various aspects of education and sociology, including the family, welfare, and aging, 1966-1993 (Box 275-302)
- Correspondence, writings, memoranda, notes, and statistical data relating to various aspects of sociological research, and especially to modernization in China and to due process of law, 1970-1996 (Box 303-349)
- Speeches and writings, correspondence, memoranda, and notes relating to various aspects of sociology, 1960-1996 (Box 350-364)
- Tables, statistical data, correspondence, memoranda, and printed matter relating to provisions for due process in constitutions of the world, 1983-1994 (Box 365-372)
- "Quality of Life" project, background material and data, 1990-1991 (Box 373-375)
  - Correlations, matrices, Eurobarometer variable list, reliability coefficient (Box 376)
  - Correlation of various traits (Box 377)
  - Regression analysis, reliability analysis (Box 378)
- Bulgarian modernization survey, 1989-1993 (Box 378)
- NIA (National Institute on Aging) grant project, methodology of convergence theory, 1985-1986 (Box 378)
- "Quality of Life" project, 1990-1991 (Box 378)
  - Data analyses, 1991 (Box 379-380)
  - Data analyses, 1990 (Box 381)
- "National Character" project, 1988-1989 (Box 382-388)
  - Draft tables; memoranda for research assistants, 1989; Notes grouped by topic, 1988-1989 (Box 382)
  - Manuscript drafts of "National Character Revisited," 1988; analyses of similar studies; Eurobarometer data (Box 383)
  - Correspondence with research assistants, 1988 (Box 384)
  - Reliability of data; test of association; regression analysis, 1988-1989 (Box 385)